Howard-von Recum Family Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Howard-von Recum Family Papers 1869-1972 (bulk 1881-1955)
MSS49395
Howard, Henry, Sir, 1843-1921
14,000 items
51 containers
20.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
British diplomat. Diaries and correspondence relating primarily to the diplomatic career of Sir Henry Howard and documenting his postings at Hague, Netherlands, the Vatican during World War I, and in China, Denmark, France, Greece, Guatemala, Russia, and the United States, also including the diaries and correspondence of his daughter, Baroness Marie Ernestine Howard von Recum, and the correspondence of his other family members and relatives.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Howard family.; Howard, Alice Lawrason, 1876-1942--Correspondence.; Howard, Cecilia Riggs, Lady, 1844-1907--Correspondence.; Howard, George, 1869-1919--Correspondence.; Howard, Henry Mowbray, 1873-1953--Correspondence.; Howard, Henry, Sir, 1843-1921.; Howard, Janet Madeleine Cecilia, 1871-1960--Correspondence.; Riggs family.; Riggs, Alice L., 1840-1927--Correspondence.; Riggs, Jane Agnes, 1854-1930--Correspondence.; Von Recum family.; Von Recum, Franz, 1906-1974--Correspondence.; Von Recum, Marie Ernestine Howard, Baroness, 1868-1954. Marie Ernestine Howard von Recum correspondence and diaries.; Von Recum, Rudolf Heinrich, Baron, 1861-1944.
Organizations
Catholic Church--Foreign relations--Great Britain.
Subjects
Aristocracy (Social class)--France.; Aristocracy (Social class)--Germany.; Aristocracy (Social class)--Great Britain.; Diplomatic and consular service, British.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945.
Places
China--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; Denmark--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; France--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; France--Social life and customs--19th century.; Germany--Social life and customs--19th century.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--Catholic Church.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--China.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--Denmark.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--France.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--Greece.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--Guatemala.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--Netherlands--Hague.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--Russia.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--United States.; Great Britain--Social life and customs--19th century.; Great Britain--Social life and customs--20th century.; Greece--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; Guatemala--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; Hague (Netherlands)--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; Russia--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; United States--Foreign relations--Great Britain.
Titles
Howard family papers; Von Recum family papers
Occupations
Diplomats.
Provenance
The papers of the Howard-von Recum family were given to the Library of Congress by Franz von Recum in 1974.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of the Howard-von Recum family are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1843, Aug. 11 Born, Berlin, Prussia
1866 1883 Posted intermittently by British foreign service to Washington, D.C.
1867 Married Cecilia Riggs (died 1907)
1871 1875 Aided in preparation of Treaty of Washington to settle Anglo-American claims Oversaw distribution of payments to United States
1874 Reposted to Hague, Netherlands
circa 1875 Served as secretary, Royal Commission on Fugitive Slaves
1883 Posted to Guatemala
1885 Posted to Greece
1886 Posted to Copenhagen, Denmark
1887 1890 Posted to Peking, China
1890 Secretary and then minister plenipotentiary, St. Petersburg, Russia
1894 Posted to Paris, France
circa 1896 circa 1908 Served at Hague, Netherlands
1899 Member British delegation, Peace Conference, Hague, Netherlands
1907 Received Order of the Bath
1914 1916 Served as first British minister to the Vatican since 1687
1921, May 4 Died, Rome, Italy
Scope and Content Note
The papers of the Howard-von Recum family span the years 1869-1972, with the bulk of the material dating from 1881 to 1955. The papers document the lives of a British diplomat and his family from the late nineteenth century, through two world wars, and into the 1950s. The papers are in English, German, and French and are organized into the following series: Diaries, Correspondence, and Addition.
The Diaries were kept by Sir Henry Howard (1843-1921) and his daughter Baroness Marie Ernestine Howard von Recum (1868-1954), with a few diary pages kept during 1914 by Lizzie Walker, a household maid. The diaries of Sir Henry Howard cover his diplomatic career from 1881 until his death. Some of the diaries sustained damage while others were lost completely during a warehouse fire in 1919. His diaries, also containing reminiscences, clippings, postcards, and ephemera, are complete for the two peace conferences he attended at Hague, Netherlands, his Peking, China, appointment from 1887-1890, and his posting to the Vatican during World War I. Events before 1881 are covered in letters to his parents especially since his father had also been a diplomat.
The diaries of Baroness Marie Ernestine Howard von Recum cover her years as a teenager posted with her family to various countries, her marriage to the German aristocrat Baron Rudolf von Recum, and the beginning of World War I. Her diaries, interleaved with photographs, clippings, and ephemera, document her family life and social and world events. The diaries may cease in 1914 because the baroness was held in protective custody by the German government during World War I.
The Correspondence documents the diplomatic life of both Sir Henry Howard and his family, the separation of family members on different sides during the world wars, and provides a glimpse into the lives of interrelated British, German, and French aristocrats. Correspondents include Sir Henry Howard, his wife Lady Cecilia Riggs Howard (1844-1907), and their children Alice Lawrason Howard (1876-1942), George Howard (1869-1919), Henry Mowbray Howard (1873-1953) known as "Pompey," Janet Madeleine Cecilia Howard (1871-1960) known as "Jessie," and Baroness Marie Ernestine Howard von Recum known as "Da." Other family members with correspondence in the papers include Franz von Recum (1906-1974), Alice L. Riggs (1840-1927), Jane Agnes Riggs (1854-1930), and other members of the Riggs family. The correspondence is arranged as it was received in three-ring binders. Although the binders are labeled as to the person and dates of correspondence enclosed, the labels do not always reflect all the persons or dates contained in a binder. At the end of the correspondence is a volume on Howard genealogy.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in three series:
Diaries, 1881-1921
Correspondence, 1869-1972
Addition, 1873-1934
Container List
- Diaries, 1881-1921 (Box 1-16)
  Diaries kept by Sir Henry Howard and Baroness Marie Ernestine Howard von Recum with a small diary kept by Lizzie Walker. Includes Sir Henry Howard's address and account books.
  Arranged by name of person and therein chronologically.
  - Howard, Henry, Sir, diaries (Box 1)
    - 1881-1887, (5 vols.) (Box 1)
    - 1887-1890, (4 vols.) (Box 2)
    - 1890-1899, (4 vols.) (Box 3)
    - 1900-1902, (3 vols.) (Box 4)
    - 1903-1904, (2 vols.) (Box 5)
    - 1905-1906, (2 vols.) (Box 6)
    - 1907-1908, (2 vols.) (Box 7)
    - 1909-1910, (4 vols.) (Box 8)
    - 1911-1913, (4 vols.) (Box 9)
    - 1913-1914, (3 vols.) (Box 10)
    - 1914-1917, (8 vols.) (Box 11)
    - 1917-1921, (6 vols.) (Box 12)
  - Recum, Marie Ernestine Howard, Baroness von ("Da"), diaries (Box 13)
    - 1883-1890, (5 vols.) (Box 13)
    - 1890-1898, (5 vols.) (Box 14)
    - 1898-1914, (4 vols.) (Box 15)
  - Howard, Henry, Sir, address and account books, undated, (2 vols.) (Box 16)
  - Walker, Lizzie, diary, 1914 (Box 16)
- Correspondence, 1869-1972 (Box 17-51)
  Letters of the Howard, von-Recum, and Riggs families, and a genealogical publication.
  Arranged as received.
  - Howard, Henry, Sir (Box 17)
    - To Henry Francis Howard and Marie Ernestine von der Schulenburg Howard (parents) (Box 17)
      - 1878-1880, (2 vols.) (Box 17)
      - 1880-1883, (2 vols.) (Box 18)
      - 1883-1885, (2 vols.) (Box 19)
      - 1893-1896, (2 vols.) (Box 20)
    - To Lady Cecilia Riggs Howard (wife) (Box 21)
      - General (Box 21)
        - 1869, 1876-1877, 1890-1894, (3 vols.) (Box 21)
        - 1905-1907, (2 vols.) (Box 22)
      - From Athens, Greece (Box 22)
        - 1885, (1 vol.) (Box 22, Box 23)
        - 1886 (Box 23)
    - To Janet Madeleine Cecilia Howard ("Jessie") (daughter), 1914-1915 (Box 23)
    - To Baroness Marie Ernestine Howard von Recum (daughter), 1880-1921, (2 vols.) (Box 24)
  - Howard, Cecilia Riggs, Lady (Box 24)
    - To Sir Henry Howard (Box 24)
      - 1883 (Box 24)
      - 1883-1884, 1895-1897, (2 vols.) (Box 25)
    - To Baroness Marie Ernestine Howard von Recum and Riggs uncles, 1881, 1894-1896, 1902-1907 (Box 25)
  - Letters of condolence on deaths of Lady Cecilia Riggs Howard and Sir Henry Howard, 1907, 1921 (Box 26)
  - Letters of condolence to Baroness Marie Ernestine Howard von Recum and letters of George Howard and Henry Mowbray Howard (sons of Sir Henry Howard and Lady Cecilia Riggs Howard), 1895-1919 (Box 26)
  - Howard, Janet Madeleine Cecilia (Box 27)
    - To Baroness Marie Ernestine Howard von Recum (Box 27)
      - 1895-1915, (3 vols.) (Box 27)
      - 1916-1920, (3 vols.) (Box 28)
      - 1920-1922, 1936-1942, (3 vols.) (Box 29)
      - 1942-1948, (2 vols.) (Box 30)
      - 1948-1951, (2 vols.) (Box 31)
      - 1952-1954, (2 vols.) (Box 32)
    - To Franz von Recum (Box 33)
      - 1915-1938, (2 vols.) (Box 33)
      - 1939-1953, (2 vols.) (Box 34)
      - 1954-1958, (3 vols.) (Box 35)
    - To Sir Henry Howard, 1915-1916 (Box 36)
  - Howard, Alice Lawrason and Janet Madeleine Cecilia Howard (daughters of Sir Henry Howard and Lady Cecilia Riggs Howard), 1914-1917 (Box 36)
  - Howard, Janet Madeleine Cecilia (Box 37)
    - Letters to Franz von Recum regarding her illness and death, 1958-1960, (2 vols.) (Box 37)
    - From Baroness Marie Ernestine Howard von Recum and letters of condolence, 1953-1954 (Box 37)
  - Howard, Alice Lawrason, 1902-1942 (Box 38)
  - Howard, Marie Ernestine von der Schulenburg, and Sir Henry Howard, 1857, 1876-1896 (Box 38)
  - Recum, Marie Ernestine Howard, Baroness von (Box 39)
    - To Franz von Recum (Box 39)
      - 1921-1932, (3 vols.) (Box 39)
      - 1933-1934, (2 vols.) (Box 40)
      - 1934-1935, (2 vols.) (Box 41)
      - 1935-1937, (3 vols.) (Box 42)
      - 1937-1939, (2 vols.) (Box 43)
      - 1939-1945, (2 vols.) (Box 44)
      - 1946-1954, (2 vols.) (Box 45)
    - War years, 1914-1918, 1939-1940, (2 vols.) (Box 46)
    - Letters received (Box 47)
      - 1877-1895, 1914-1921, (3 vols.) (Box 47)
      - 1910-1942, 1950 (Box 48)
    - Eightieth birthday and Christmas, 1948-1953 (Box 48)
  - Riggs family, 1881, 1888 (Box 49)
  - Riggs, Alice L. and Jane Agnes, 1890-1921, (3 vols.) (Box 50)
  - Recum, Franz von, Ancestry and Descendance of Sir Henry Francis Howard, 1809-1898, 1972, (2 vols.) (Box 51)
- Addition, 1873-1934 (Box 51)
  Sermon and printed matter.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Printed matter (Box 51)
    - List of Claims of British Subjects against the United States, and American Citizens against Great Britain, 1873 (Box 51)
    - Royal Commission on Fugitive Slaves: Memorandum on the Treaties Concluded by Great Britain with Powers Still Owning Slaves for the Suppression of the Slave Trade, and on the Status of Slavery in Those Countries, 1876 (Box 51)
  - Sermon at consecration of Chapel of Our Lady and St. Teresa on Friday Street built by Alice Lawrason Howard, Painswick, Gloucestershire, England, photocopy, circa 1934 (Box 51)